two one welcome to voices with verveiki
i'm uh joined by uh by gary shang
uh gary reached out to me not that long
ago uh because he was very interested in
my work
because he found a lot of resonance
between my work and the very important
work he's doing
at civics unplugged um and so welcome
gary why don't you tell us
about uh what you're doing at civix
unplugged please
yeah thanks so much john for having me
um
so after graduating from duke in
uh 2015 i uh
i got a i got a full-time job as a
software engineer at google
and um you know it's easy for me to
admit now because i'm kind of
over that hump but uh or the meaning
the lack of meaning hub but my two main
goals
uh when when going to new york were
basically to go to fun
parties and to climb the corporate
ladder right almost like
ruthlessly and um
2016 right we all know what happened
there were a few major elections in the
world
um and it really shattered my
understanding of just my confidence and
how i understood the world
um and so i i think like a lot of people
whose
understanding of of their own
understanding uh
like a lot of people whose
understandings got shattered because of
you know extraordinary events that they
couldn't predict uh they turned they
turned to where
a lot of people were learning i'd like
to uh
say that the default civic education for
people today is twitter
which is like the worst place that you
can develop a civic education because
like
the good the greatest civic education is
a moral education it's a character
uh developing education um it's a
it's one where you where where well i'm
to borrow
your own language it's like you develop
personhood through
real real deep contextualized
relationships in dialogue
right and so the joke that i made um
the last time we chatted was that
um 140 characters is the kind of the
exact opposite of uh an authentic
dialogues which is why i'm i'm just
i'm kind of obsessed with your uh your
die logo series because
well my mind goes a lot of places and
we'll get to that
but um for for
for many months after after the 2016
election
um i was just like scouring uh
twitter and following a bunch of people
that have had a lot of big followings
looking at articles that they were
reading not really no
understanding just how how much it was
polluting my
um you know maybe users were differently
like information ecology in my own brain
right and and i felt like i was like oh
this is it
right there there's this there's good
and there's this evil
right how do i fit in how do i you know
fight
um this evil and
ultimately i uh was able to
[Music]
um work with some you know
big activists that that wanted help from
from smart people
and in the course of from the spring of
2017 to the spring of 2018
i don't know if we talked about this
actually um i was able to help
this this group get a billion
impressions on facebook
yeah and so you know a big part of at
least how i've been informed by your
work is
you know feedback loops mind viruses
memetic almost warfare
um and uh at some point i just
i just uh like i i actually
the way that i accidentally opened my
mind
to just order started to realize just
how
polluted my information ecology was was
i wanted to study
the other sides how they thought
so i could be better at at the warfare
and it turned out that as soon as i
started to to listen to
the media that they were putting out
there just just to just to get their
perspective
i was like this actually makes a lot of
sense like or like
i get it like like a lot of it is um
by the way i i checked out well i'm
actually in the middle of reading
zack stein's uh um
education uh i'm messing up the title
in between worlds right and i
yeah in time between two worlds and i
it's funny last night i was actually
googling
your two names together i was like hmm
these two people should talk
and i'm happy yeah turns out so so i
listened to one of those which is
um it was it was pretty fabulous
but um back back to
kind of back back to my journey
uh i
i started to to realize
just how dangerous the
um dangerous almost like the
the world system is if you don't have
i guess psycho technologies to real
just to just to even understand how to
navigate
right right right like like what is
i mean there's so much there's so much
that you have to
um process in order to
and even you have to develop ways of
processing information not just
i remember you saying in one of your
recent conversations that it's not just
information access it's about
how you process that information which
is the difference and
and i and i'm you know living proof that
you know once you change the way that
you process information
um you're able to see things a lot a lot
more clearly
so i the reason why i stopped doing that
whole
facebook social media i stopped playing
that game well one because i realized it
was a game
where you're actually uh it's a zero-sum
uh like everyone loses sort of game
right and um it was actually
and i was losing as well right i was i
was becoming more reactive
i was becoming uh i was becoming
skeptical of
everyone around me right including
including my like it was it was changing
my fundamental orientation
right as a person right and i didn't
like what i was seeing in the mirror
like and and that i guess i'm still i'm
proud of myself for
even acknowledging that because um you
know
i think we should talk about you know
the the
like the value systems that like social
media perpetuates and how like
we i mean gdp is a single metric right
number of followers single metric these
actually change the way that you see the
world
right in a way that is extremely
dangerous and unnatural
so i i did the hard thing i cut that
cold turkey and i
this wasn't like a this wasn't just like
serial
where i just started doing research like
i said i started to inadvertently open
my mind
and then you know thousands of hours of
exploration later um well
one of the amazing things that i'm glad
to have stumbled on
was your awakening from the meaning
crisis series which
uh deeply informed what i would do next
after google
which i was so i was doing this all
while i was
a full-time software engineering lead on
google cloud
and um your your series uh
really helped me will make sense of
uh what i went through like i i i
like i think because people really need
to
make sense of themselves in the grand in
in some sort of meta-narrative
um it's very easy for people to prey on
people that don't have
that that don't know where they fit into
yeah
the world right yeah well said so um
so i can pause there before talking
because
because i thought i just felt like the
back story would be helpful for
well for you and for uh viewers
no no that was very helpful um um
and thank you for what you said and i'm
i'm glad to know that my series
uh was so uh helpful to you
so it sounds like you get this sort of
socratic emporia
everything comes into question deep
state of wonder
and then you do this pivot and and so
what comes after the pivot
what did you move into great so um
so we kind of like to joke
that we are um a
a spiritual movement or civ
religion that is not a religion
disguised as a civic leadership
program because
like it's a
and and one thing that i've i've i've
realized
a lot is that you you have to get people
to come with what they already find
meaningful or they think that they find
meaningful
like right right and then they so it's
like you come for
the kind of tactical oh like i now know
how to
do this as a leader but like then you're
like oh like
i'm in community now yes other really
good people
that i get to dialogue with and i get to
grow with and i get to be vulnerable
with and like
i actually get to shape my identity
through
uh this vulnerable exchange authentic
exchange
where um it's funny because i was
i was i have uh i guess participatory
knowledge and perspectival knowledge of
the power of dialogue and and your
series actually helped me understand um
that that wasn't a fluke and that that
other
you know other people like uh
it's it's almost like so obvious now
that that that a
dialogue is the way that that you under
it's like this
this conversation already is so far from
like
what other people may assume a dialogue
is like
let me get my word in and then like
there's information that
it's like this is this is already really
rewarding for me
um in a uh like
it's already it's i'm already feeling
very uplifted but anyways
um so so
the main narrative that we
um explain and this it's true but
there's so much more to that
is that like democracy is in crisis in
america right and
and there's been movements uh there's
been like
lots of people that have been trying to
reform our democracy
build it anew for decades right and well
i mean
as long as our as our political system
has or democracy has been around
which i could argue has never really
been a democracy for
for everyone uh you i don't think you
can point to a single time in american
history where
it's actually been a great experience
for for
every every type of person um
but but uh i think the veterans of the
democracy
reform movement in america will be the
first to admit
it's extremely monolithic right it's
um it's lacking in um
uh all sorts of diversity especially
young people
especially young women and and we
and a lot a lot of this was actually
unintentional like we we never had any
quotas
but when we were recruiting for our our
first leadership development fellowship
in january of this year we ended up
getting 80 percent
uh young women majority that doesn't
surprise
the internet right and uh like
leadership development programs i don't
know if you've
ever heard of boyce state for example no
i haven't
so it's like this it's it's become
really famous
for creating simulations of uh of
elections
right so like they basically they
randomly assign people into two parties
and then they have like the whole point
is for
people to decide who who gets elected
right and i'm
and there's a documentary by the way and
i'm like watching this and i'm like
uh like you know
[Music]
what that immediately made me think of
was are you talking about
um philo nikea
versus what's the other one filo sofia
sophia right yes exactly right right
yeah and like
the fact that the simulation ends after
you've won the election
is like are you kidding me right like
like
this is actually people specific again
so civic education let's recap
is well i didn't say this is government
government approved
education which um why would the
government teach you how to make
it better or change it or overthrow any
part of it right
right or it's twitter which is all about
information warfare or it's um extremely
heralded
organizations like boy state and look i
think there's benefit because it's like
it actually is like oh like it's like oh
okay this is what
it like it's actually kind of ruthless
and um
right some of it's like a lot of it's
just about charisma it's like i think
that's important
to understand but and so it's not about
like okay we shouldn't do this it's like
what else right there needs to be other
sorts of
um i don't even want to say simulation
just like other experiences that they're
like oh okay
this is what the social fabric should
feel like right right right right
um and so what would i uh
what i would um so ultimately
what well well there's no ultimate
one of the things that we're trying to
do at civix unplugged is
uh equip young people to be the
the inspiring democracy builders that
are are missing um right
but the thing that we didn't plan for
was that the the way that we have
organized
our kids to will be kind of
like intrinsically motivated to stay
organized
is like well it's your project as well
right it's like
um have you are you familiar with
maybe a dumb question uh with ben
franklin's june toes
no no no so i don't know how
at what frequency he gathered like a
group of um
his like like kindred spirits almost but
like at a
recurring frequency he would gather a
group of people
to talk about uh issues that they're
facing
and issues that the civil society is
and actually try to uh
like take on challenges together right
right cool
and so what we've done at civic's
unplugged
is uh uh
stand-up junetoes for our kids
um so so so we had we had this training
period
from january to july but now it's
literally like
until like infinity they are now they're
in junetoes among other things
um they're in junto's and like it was
maybe i should be surprised or not just
like this
pure dynamic of so i would i
i like i helped stand up these groups
initially just
to show them okay this is how you would
facilitate here's how you how you
you know here's how you get through the
agenda once they got it very quickly
and now they're just self-sustaining
groups of peers wow
that that the whole point is just to
talk about whatever is meaningful
and that like have take on
optional time to debug an issue that
they're facing
right right and and this is
it's helpful for you and any uh viewers
to hear that they're not getting any
sort of thing like this
anywhere else in their life right right
yeah but
i think there's like a level of you know
they're filtering their experience when
they're talking to their
their parents even their siblings even
their even their
friends which are friends of uh
convenience often
right to kind of uh you know there's all
these different types of threats right
and and these are these are these might
be their first
friends of good right right right right
yeah
yeah the co-cultivation character and
and so they're
they're actually like they're able to
[Music]
um they're almost like able to get into
flow state for the
for the first time in terms of an
interpersonal right um
right yeah yeah because they they're
able there's like oh
it's rewarded to talk about um
whatever it feels meaningful and it's
like it's like this
extremely auxiliary experience
especially given the context of
parental pressures and also quite
honestly
prison-like conditions in their k-12
systems
right and i don't use i don't use that
that kind of analogy lightly
um especially it's especially the case
in the covet times
where they are they're super super
regimented but that was also the case
uh uh before where where it's not about
what they want to do it's about what um
a uh any number of
uh of of of entities that have co-opted
the education system right right right
so
um i'll pause there because i know i've
said a lot but
i want you to this is yeah it's really
good
to be um you know connected with you
because
there's there's just like an infinite
menu of like
connection points because
[Music]
probably because uh your whole project
is meaning right and yeah uh
you know it what i've
what i've really realized is
it takes a long time
to to change entrenched systems and if
the
if the if the
these are not exact synonyms but people
use them like synonyms so i'll just use
them
so if the movement community change
making force
that is trying to change a system is not
a deeply rewarding
flow-inducing experience yeah it's not
going to sustain
and and this is my my common critique
with with political movements yeah
movement
right that they dissipate as soon as the
election's over
yes yeah wait what a waste of like it's
almost like
they pay people to just be there for an
election it's like wait
don't you realize that if you were able
to create and this is very hard so i get
i understand why
they they don't do this and they're or
they're unable to do this but like
if you're able to create um kind of
like a real community that
is intrinsically motivated to support
each other and to support
and to further uh realize a vision or an
a mission
um
you're able to to mobilize that
community
for for a long time right because
because it's because
because strengthening protecting
strengthening
reimagining reinvent reinventioning
uh things uh it is not it's not about
a giant overhaul right for for any
reason it's about like
being able to to see leverage points
and like yeah you know shift parameters
in parallel
shift the parameters in parallel exactly
and what you're talking about
is not trying to
i would say in my language i would say
you're ultimately not trying to
even bring about a political change uh
you're actually trying to
bring about a cultural change which is
the
the grounding way of being and the
underlying normativity
the soil in which a democracy has to be
rooted
right yes 100 and the soil and and i
i love that you brought that up because
um i was working with a group of
the kids and they're and they're
brilliant right like
like kids when they're able to
uh and i and i know that you have this
experience just like i do
when the mission is big enough you get a
lot smarter
right yeah yeah yeah yeah yeah and when
you feel like
okay i have an important role to play in
kind of fulfilling this achieving this
mission uh
like it's just like what like this is
and you thought you weren't curious you
thought you weren't
uh extremely smart and creative um
we put our kids in situations where they
know
almost everything is a bs academic
exercise
that is meant to fill space and check
certain boxes for an administrator
right right and so and so what when
they're when they're finally put
into i mean there's all this pent up
like energy to like do good
right into and to grow um
and to ask meaningful questions and and
pursue them
uh it's it's been a really uh
you know you know this well right
because you have
um you have supported a lot of
really great thinkers and i'm going to
get um
his name wrong christopher mai meister
pietro
christopher you're a friend yes and i
was just watching
um uh one of your conversations
uh that was like kind of hosted by
andrew sweeney oh andrew's great yes
yeah
yeah he's so like it's he's like a
master class in curiosity
yeah yeah um and like just talking about
art
and how it like uh
i mean it just allows you to see you
know
reality more clearly and just from
different angles right because you have
to see
you have to see the same thing from a
lot of different angles so that you're
not
well you're almost like not bullshitting
yourself right exactly
exactly so so
that was so i just wanted to
um i don't want to lose a threat about
the soil because
uh so so my point of bringing up the
kids well there's a lot of reasons
because they're amazing
but uh they they were the ones that were
pushing
for like imagine there's like a civic
world that has been
gravely um i mean it's just
just been malnourished to say the least
and
it's not if not just like actively
slashed right and it's like so there's a
rainforest
where like the soil right which includes
like
you know what nutrients include
information right and culture
right and valley like what and like
what's cool right so what's cool right
now
is to virtue signal what's cool is to
distort what other
people are saying um so that your side
wins and again like
there are deep roots of the culture
um you know i think people people really
like to point to very simple
explanations for
for why things are bad right like like
an organization like boy state has been
around for uh since like 1920 or
something
oh really yeah and so it's been it's
been
there's this legacy of like really
celebrating wow good job
you won you you you you convinced a lot
of kids
that you should um be elected right and
then again the simulation ends so like
like the way that we orient ourselves to
the world has been
enculturated for for what for way longer
i've realized
than than uh you know the introduction
of mark zuckerberg's rise in in the
world right
right um this is we are just we are
actually we are living in unprecedented
times where
um the kind of uh
for lack of a better term the worst in
us is being magnified
yeah uh algorithmically in a way that
um it's it's kind of mind-boggling and
and you're
you're actually going to be unable to to
understand exactly how
until you completely unplug which um
i will say we we did not we were not
that intentional
about uh civics um the unplugged part
but it's like unplug
unplugging from the simulation like so
oh my like we got so lucky with that
name
right right right yeah because it's all
about that right and it's like
people ask what's civics it's like it's
like whatever it takes
to unplug from what's not meaningful
and plug into what's meaningful that's
our that
that sort of and it's like because that
project is so
um big and open-ended and
and honestly dialectic right like you're
like someone's someone's
definition of what's meaningful and
definition of what's worth building
in the world uh it's they're not going
to be the same and i think
i think we need to find a way to
uh raise children
right and develop civ citizen leaders
that that
that enjoy dialectic uh enjoy enjoy the
process of dialoguing with
with people that are different than them
right
because these are maybe this is you
again right which
shows is how much i have i've gotten
from you and i've transformed through
you
um but like there are
uh there are kind of irresolvable
values conflicts about like you know
pro-life
and pro-choice like we act like there's
going to be
one day people are going to wake up and
like there's one
like once we start realizing that like
they're
um there are extremely valid reasons for
holding
uh certain positions uh
and and that we we're actually and
perhaps most importantly
that the political media technology
industrial complex is weaponizing
these irresolvable conflicts yeah
because it sells
yeah because it sells because it gets us
really mad
once we realize once we're able to step
outside that we're like
oh okay so at least we can unite
and that's kind of the point of of at
least my personal focus
on uh democracy reform which a lot of
people
a lot of people uh perhaps rightfully
assume that it's like about electoral
stuff it's like no it's about
culture it's about yes um it's about
technology
it's about it's about everything that is
harming us from actually building
the civic world which uh which itself is
like okay what would the civic world be
great let's talk about it
and i think i think that's that's one of
the first steps
wow that that's that's amazing i i
i just want to just keep listening to
you and your passion
and your insight are fantastic
and so can you tell us a little bit more
about sort of the practicalities of it i
get the idea that this sort of starts
out
and you draw people in uh like as a
civics
uh course of course on how uh civil so
how civics works and
what this what it is to be a citizen etc
and then that moves into
you know around leadership and all
initially obviously there's some
uh practical skills that are being
taught and then you leave that
that evolves naturally and draws them
into
you know the cultivation of wisdom
meaning character virtue so what what
age group are we talking about for these
kids
and what does the program sort of look
like yeah
it's 14 to uh 18 although you know
they they get older right and and we're
we're here to support them
for and exactly how we support them is
an evolutionary thing
but what we basically committed to is
like everything that you need
to uh like we're here to support you and
everything that you need
to uh build that civic world
and uh because i think that like people
uh like
people kind of shoot like organizations
people kind of shoot themselves in the
foot by being overly specific about the
how
and not about like the ultimate
why and then the and then the what um
so the fellowship which runs every year
the the second year starts in uh january
um it involves uh
uh involves the the kids learning in a
very participatory way
personal development systems thinking
community building
and democratic theory
and every one of the lessons is is
communal and
participatory uh like
it's very very questions oriented so
like
we'll post a question in a kind of live
lecture
sort of thing and then everyone gets to
see the answers of everyone else
right right and then
we'll talk about it and then then we as
like kind of the instructors will share
like our
our answer but like with the caveat that
it's like
you know everyone else's answers made
sense as well like you know
yes for the most part right um and then
because we realized that um
i mean well so much of just developing
and
developing self-awareness is
understanding like the
almost like landscape of of human
possibility i get like like what you're
saying
like what what what could
people answer this question with and
it's like really fast it's super it's
fascinating for me
right it's fascinating for kids to
answer like so so even the questions
like what are you struggling with
right and then like you get this you get
this mosaic of answers there's lots of
patterns
there's lots of kind of edge cases and
you're like oh okay that increases your
empathy
um it it shows that there's other people
that are dealing with similar issues
um and that's i think like
a big part of even therapy right is just
like even acknowledging that
uh or group therapy is just even even if
you don't
resolve an issue um just like getting it
out in the world and also knowing that
you're not alone in something right
right
there's there's something um
like calming about that right like
there's something
yeah so i'll get you out of the
perspective it gives you
at least the other person's perspective
on your perspective gives you a room
like the the the pretended pretentious
inevitability of a of a perspective is
challenged
just by the presence of an alternative
exterior perspective
yes yes um
and and it's it's so clear again from
the experience so
so we actually put uh kids in in groups
and juntos of of eight uh eight to ten
uh like right away starting in in
february
and then there they those junetoes meet
every week
um again they're
really really enriching experiences for
the kids because
uh almost all of their interactions it's
sad to say uh are transactional
yeah yeah outside of civics unplugged
right and actually yeah and a lot of and
some of the kids
literally call uh our digital world
kind of in oasis and and and what what
i like to say is it's our job to turn
this
oasis which again it's like surrounded
by desert a civic desert let's say
uh and turn it uh turn it into a lush
rainforest that that spreads across
multiple continents
that's wonderful image wonderful image
uh and and that's and that's honestly
like how i see uh
your die logo series like
what i see is uh
people that needed to find each other
finding each other
yes yes that's well put
and and as smart as uh i don't
i don't like that word smart but as as
as fine off as you would be
let's say to just be reading books on
your own right and
and coming up with and almost
monologuing
right to a receptive audience um
i've noticed that you uh it's very
helpful for you
to to see that other people are
converging
on similar conclusions about the world
right or just yeah
they're very helpful yeah extreme
they're coming to
similar insights especially if well
it doesn't strike me that you know you
try to bring that many people that are
just
you know blindly take on ideas from
other people on your channel so it's
like
it's like okay from if you bring on a
bunch of first principles thinkers
and and you just talk about what their
their kind of
thought projects are and there's a lot
of convergence it's like
okay uh let's work together to figure
out
how to address this meeting crisis so
one of the things that we realized as an
organization is
um a a huge part of the benefit
of of what we're doing is the kind of
intimate size
of yeah of our community so right now
it's about 200
um a fraction of those people
uh show up right into the virtual space
to engage uh every day and but but we
but
uh we we have some real life like
superheroes
like like like real life like like
i was thinking like okay if this person
was
able to uh
like their stories were able to be
followed um
by like uh
like random random middle schoolers for
example
that that would transform the middle
schoolers
or you know for that matter really
anyone's perspective of what what they
could
see as possible because these are really
remarkable kids and
um so so we have this little oasis
that has some remarkable like like
basically super like real life superhero
kids with like they have that much
potential
and um then you have this extremely
powerful
uh well there's no single technology but
let's look at netflix when netflix is
able to
kind of put its you know camera right on
like a particular phenomenon everyone
can know about it
right so um
you know i don't want to jinx this right
but
one one of the things that we're trying
to work on is to put our organization in
a position
where um it's
it's a uh kind of
mutually rewarding proposition for
someone like netflix or disney plus
right to to follow
yeah of of these
real-life young civic superheroes um who
embody basically the they are like
almost like living embodiments
of the culture that we that you and i
know need to be just like
people even need to need to be aware of
uh and
hopefully inspired by but but by just
like
you know and and what what what would
this
um react like true reality tv
hopefully show that like these kids are
having real dialogue
with with people to learn about the
world and their minds are being opened
like as they're as they're speaking um
they're actually
constantly questioning their beliefs
they're working on extremely important
projects
they're not they're not focused on
uh you know the context-free social
media
um and so like
just kind of summarize our goal is not
to
try to get uh millions of people into
the intimate sort of program that we
have it's to
put a spotlight on uh
you know on on
the like real life and i'm very
intentional with the word superhero
because what is the what is the main
thing
that it's almost like what what what are
some of the few things that like
almost everyone in the population has
right they've watched a superhero movie
right like from kids kids to to old like
all sorts of
race gender whatever um and so we we
need those
sort of stories and they can't just be
pure fiction right it can't just be uh
iron man
like while there's real what life kind
of
like lessons about courage that come
from
you know star wars or avengers right
like
people need to people really need people
are actually people
are already hungry hungering for for
um basically a blueprint for how they
can be
uh like a superhero right
right and like gen z especially right
and you see this with
um their massive marches which i think
it's like
what what that makes me excited about is
that
there's this intent to do a lot of good
there's a lot of work that needs to be
done to show what it actually takes
it takes a ton of
it takes a lot of time it takes a lot of
curiosity
and and and hard work to understand
what a system that you want to shift
uh is so that you can actually shift it
in a way that
uh hopefully does not create more
unintended consequences
right that are bad instead of good which
is which is kind of like the story of
public policy
of the past i don't know like at least
40 years
right and and right now we're we're
choosing between two candidates that
um they both have have done things that
narratively made sense at the time but
they they have
produced pretty tremendous uh
you know tremendously bad consequences
so joe biden right
uh you know i just want to be fair here
uh because we we can talk about trump
all we want but joe biden
uh i don't know if you know that he
authored the crime bill
that was foundational to mass
incarceration
uh of in america right
and i don't want to impugn anyone's
intentions
i think that it just it almost felt like
an inevitability at a time
like from what i've read it's like of
course we have to
deal with these super predators we need
to secure our cities
like law and order right it just felt
like inevitably and this is the power of
culture i think that's changed
so much which which gives me a lot of
optimism
and i think the social media and just
the media landscape in general allows
for
quick much quicker dissemination of
culture then
what did you say steal the culture
so uh a big part of what
uh we're trying to do is to steal the
culture for a small group of people
that we can then shine a spotlight on
and then steal the culture for
like the whole world that that's just a
fantastic plan
gary and that's just i mean i mean i
i haven't had much to say because i just
wanted to listen to you
i mean just so thoughtful and insightful
and exciting right um
and i mean it just um i i mean i want to
do whatever i can to
help support this i mean obviously i'm
going to put out this video it'd be
great to
maybe have you come back you know first
and talk more about this and say more
what's going on for sure
yeah i'd love to bring one of the kids
that would be fantastic
yep oh what a great idea gary yep oh i
would love that
oh i would love that very much fantastic
but john i i just don't see another way
like i i i i
in terms of that that that plan right
because we
um it's i've re i've realized that
whatever we're doing in this oasis is
is not is not scalable at any at any
pace that is necessary to move the
culture at a pace
that allows for so let me um
let me like so so i care about a a lot
of issues
the kids care about a lot my whole the
whole team cares about life issues right
education democracy the
the corruption of our political system
and our political culture
is is preventing us from doing anything
right and
just so you know that the timetable of
how fast or slow and i'm saying slow uh
like electoral reforms government
reforms take is that like
even so we have a ballot initiative in
florida that is to
open primaries basically there's a
primary system before a general election
the primaries are basically corrupt
co-op co-opted and
you know selected behind the scenes by
parties so that independents third
parties
can't really have their say on who ends
up getting the general election
and so there's a ballot initiative in
florida basically a citizens movement to
allow for more types of uh
like just feasibly allow for more uh
more choice before the general election
and even if that passes
do you have a guess of of when it it
goes into effect
i don't know 10 years all right so i i
think i
2024 right but even even even with 2024
it's not like it's like without
without the proper culture to go along
with it and even just through awareness
that that that is not crazy anymore
right for an independent to run right
and independent's not going to run
because people are
because it's about it's like i mean
i know this too well right because it's
actually paralyzing to do things
where you you think that even just like
a few people in your life that
you think that matter will be like is he
crazy oh he finally he's finally
lost his [ __ ] right like he's like you
know he like
and what we can talk about maybe another
time but the difference between
being a visionary and a delusional
person is like
uh in my opinion is like access to
resources and
and connections so so
um you know
anyways uh it it so it's like
let's say we want to do any of the
things that zack stein wants
um in terms of education system that
works way better than it does
right we have to drastically reform
and just reimagine and reinvent
uh the the the the social and political
kind of soil right that uh allows for us
to even talk about education ideas
yes exactly exactly and so we have to
think about things in
i hate to say this and i i've had to
grapple with this on my own
we have to think in decade-long time
scales because
um it's sort of like it's a it's an
oversimplification but it's a helpful
one
where it's like it's we have to get our
our soil correct
before new new trees of education right
can can actually flourish
which which is going to be we're going
to take a lot of time but um
i guess to kind of close this whole loop
is
um i don't i don't know what
what you expected from putting out
the series that that that you did
um but
it it just had a it's such a profound
kind of influence on
my my development and
and uh the the organizations that i work
with just the philosophy that i operate
in life um well
well what i wanted to do is i let's play
with the metaphor i wanted to turn over
the soil i wanted to till it i wanted to
fertilize it
as much as possible that's why i'm doing
all that all the series
you know awakening for the meeting
crisis voices with verveiki
untangling the world not that the ones
that are coming down the pipe
that's why you know chris you mentioned
chris uh chris and i have put together
uh an anthology of all the people well
at least no sorry that's too bold many
of the major players in this whole
dialogue movement and all these
communities of practices
and trying to get one of the things is
to try and get like
you know what we need to do i we need to
shine the spotlight on the oasis
but we also have to get all the oasis
connected by trade routes
yes all you know all trading ideas and
trading practices with each other
could not agree more um you know jordan
hall
um has been deeply
uh you know
uh influential in my in my own thinking
um god why is why is my memory failing
who who's who's who's the uh who's doing
the consilience project
uh he he has he has a long
daniel schmucktenberger
also a really uh clear thinker about
this i loved your magic
dialogue yes so yeah
so good because um
i guess one of the things i think a lot
a lot about it's like
it doesn't matter if it's
for words are so limiting so it doesn't
matter if it's not real right
if it's useful right like this feeling
that there is magic
in the world is like it it actually does
produce
a lot of what you would think would
happen if there was
magic in the in the world yeah symbolic
action serious play
are things that we have to well take
seriously again yeah jun sun
he's a former student of mine and you
know now one of my tas and ras
manager he's doing i'm just so proud of
the work he's doing it's just amazing
work
it's amazing also paul vander clay yeah
paul vanderbilt's doing
jonathan yeah yeah
there's just and like you already
mentioned andrew sweeney
uh you know and zach stein there's just
a whole
uh a whole bunch of people i mean and i
got to talk to some of the seminal
figures
i got to talk to james karst which was
amazing
right that infinite is that infinite
game yeah and uh religious gates against
belief
unfortunately we lost james yesterday
oh passed away uh which is very sad
i'm so glad that i got to interact with
him on a car
on a couple of occasions i'm so happy
about our most recent
uh because we were both on fire and so
um
just to have that for me not for him but
for me
that final deal logos with him that just
caught fire
that was just such a wonderful blessing
and a gift i i deeply appreciate of it
well gary i should get going
uh but uh but um like
i definitely okay so your proposal let's
let's make it
let's make it happen i want to have
another discussion with you and i want
you to bring one of your kids on
or you know and and let's i want to hear
more i want to open up more i want to
shine the spotlight
i want to do everything you're talking
about let's do it and let's do it after
uh the election yeah no i i was going to
propose
we have plenty of uh i don't want to say
fun but there's going to be a lot of
interesting meaningful things
to discuss uh in early early
mid-november
so why don't we plan for something like
that yeah so let's plan for that that's
fantastic
and um i mean i just want you you you've
said a lot of
complimentary things about me i just
want to say i want to compliment you
back
you are realizing and you know what i
what that i mean a lot by that word
you are realizing what i'm talking about
in a deep
like in a deep and you know actual
you know rubber hitting the roadway and
that i'm so deeply impressed by it so
deeply impressed by it
i i just uh just to kind of reference
it it's funny um
you've really taught me the the
uh the power of analyzing words really
carefully and using words really
carefully so
what i do is i appreciate your work
ah well said wow
it's not as oh yeah cool it's like i i
really
okay this is there's some there's some
there's a reason
why like this man is dedicating
so much energy because i i i don't i'm
sure you've talked about this somewhere
but like
you're awakening from the meeting crisis
series
and all the series it just shows
like i'm sure well let's talk about the
awakening for the meeting credit series
probably
you probably spent like thousands of
hours like just well
at least at least the course i mean even
if you put it together at a certain
number of hours it's like this is
this is this is a lifelong sort of thing
that that you yeah
you're like oh like this is this is
going to help a lot of people
and and um i guess the the thing that
i just to plant this seed uh with you
and maybe this is like an
ongoing project that we can work on is
like how do we make
um the most essential
uh kind of elements of of your work and
i guess all of our
our work um accessible
to as many people as possible that's
that's uh
yeah paul vander clay has i mean
in addition to convergence deal logos
carries within it
the true scaffolding and affordance of
constructive criticism and that's a
point that paul
has made um vis-a-vis the comparison to
the traditional religions and i think
that is one of the central questions
that we need to keep coming back to
again
and again and i think we need an ongoing
evolving answer
and you can see me discussing this also
with jordan jordan hall
we need an ongoing evolving answer that
is continually to you know continually
producing emergent aspects of a response
to that question
uh because i don't think we're going to
get oh right here here's that i don't
think there's an algorithm
to answer that question i think i think
also
it has to be something uh that will very
much take on a life of its own
uh in how it's how that problem is
addressed
uh but i do i do let me return
again um to you i deeply appreciate the
way you are exemplifying
so much and you're doing like and you
did like on your own
like i'm not taking any credit for this
whatsoever
the way you you you so clearly exemplify
so much of you know what i'm talking
about and what i'm trying to achieve and
i
deeply i'm deeply grateful for that
well i'm grateful for you and grateful
for this opportunity to
well to meet you again and dialogue and
uh and make this an ongoing dialogue uh
for that matter well i think that's
fantastic
gary i mean i'm glad we had this and i
look forward to the one after the
election
i hope feels like as peacefully as
possible
um oh hope hopefully yeah
um and uh please maybe in an email send
me any
any information you want me to put into
the description of this video
sounds good i i uh i have a lot of
i mean the rabbit hole goes deep uh of
just at least send me some of the the
choices
links you think i should well so i i
want to send you some other stuff
outside of what you would put in a blurb
as well because okay
i'll do both all right thank you thank
you so so much
all right